Hello everybody, and welcome
to the content video going
over section 1.6 of your
textbook, operating systems.
So we're just gonna talk a
little bit about operating
systems, some of the main
ones and how they run.
So an operating system is what works
with your software on your computer,
connects it to the hardware.
We kind of talked about that
in the content video going
over hardware and software.
So in another video, we talked
about high level languages,
assembly languages, and machine
languages, And what really happens is
once your software turns code into
machine code, or once your code
turns into that, or once your
software is translated into that, the
operating system then takes the machine
code and sends it down to the CPU.
So that's kind of what this section
is talking about right here.
So I probably said in one of the
other videos that your code is taken
down a level from, let's say, a
high-level language and then taken
down another level until it gets
to machine language or binary. but
really it's the operating system
that sends your code to the CPU.
So like I said the CPU allows
software to work together with the
hardware or sorry the operating
system allows software to work
together with the hardware. So there
are three main operating systems
and you've probably heard of all
of them. There's Windows, Linux
and if we scroll down a little bit
further Apple Mac OS And there's
more, but we'll just talk about
these three for just a moment.
I run Windows personally. You can
probably see it on this video recording.
A lot of you probably run
it as well. The second
most common one is going
to be Apple or Mac OS.
And if you're running Linux,
that's awesome. Kudos to
you. One day I want to run
a Linux operating system.
I just have not gotten
around to setting one up yet.
But I think that they're really
cool in that they're actually
fairly really good if you're in
a development or a software or a
data engineering position. I
think that they're great for that.
One thing I want to talk about really
quick is the difference between a
proprietary operating system and an
open source operating system. So a
proprietary operating system like
Windows means that it's owned by like
the like one head company and they're
the ones who are developing it.
They're the ones who are controlling
it, releasing updates, etc, etc.
And And Windows is a proprietary
operating system because Windows
takes care of all of the updates.
They run the operating system. They
take care of everything. It's
controlled by Microsoft exclusively.
So something like Linux is open
source, meaning that it's actually
the community that upkeeps it and
develops it and manages it. So
what's interesting is you think that
if it's just the community running
something, that it actually would
probably fall apart. I mean, I've
seen the community basketball pit
or core or whatever. it's not very
good right but the one that's
owned by the university that's that
one's great I really like playing
basketball at that one right so
what's the difference between a
proprietary operating system versus
an open source one well it happened
what really happens is that there
are so many people who use something
like Linux that it actually
gets scrutinized all the time and
so if something's not working right
or something's not good enough the
community really comes together
and actually fixes errors a lot
quicker and sometimes a lot better
than a proprietary operating system.
Because if you think about it,
well, they got to wait
for funding or maybe they
got to wait for a big
patch update or something.
And so an open source operating
system like Linux is really open
to the community of coders to
continue to adapt it and change
it as they see fit. So like you
could even join the people who
are developing Linux right now
and you could actually make
changes that are to the benefit
of everyone. And it's up to you.
Let's scroll down a little bit.
There's a lot of open-source communities.
Python is open-source.
Hopefully, you recognize GitHub
as being something that you've
used at least once for this
class, and that's open-source as
well. There's a couple more in here,
but Python and GitHub and Linux
are probably three of the most
common open-source softwares.
We'll scroll down a little
bit further to Mac OS here.
so there's a little bit of a story
about mac os that if you're super
interested you can read about here
but basically apple was founded by
steve jobs and steve wozniak and
through a lot of different decisions
that they both made mac os came
into existence um it's actually
interesting i think it was uh yeah
steve jobs thought that microsoft was
gonna or was like feeling threatened
by Microsoft he's like oh no
that's a really up-and-coming company
it's better than ours what do we
do right and well you guys can tell
me whether or not you think Microsoft
is better than macOS I don't
have an opinion on this I've used
them both but then eventually he
came back to Apple and there's this
whole thing about Next Incorporated
and then eventually it just became
Apple's macOS operating system and
so it's a descendant of this next
step or next incorporated operating
system and it's used on most Apple
products so if you have an iPhone
and Apple Watch I don't think many
people have iPods anymore but oh
that's an iPad my bad I have an
iPod and an iPad so I guess I just
still love my iPod Touch I think we
peaked when the iPod Touch was the
pinnacle of technology so um and
yeah that's oh actually let's talk
about the kernel for a second i
think i skipped over that so the the
kernel is uh actually kind of like
the core code that runs your
operating system and um you know what
you're probably thinking there's code
that runs my code yeah it's inception
code i guess code that runs code
it's a little bit complicated.
But if you think about that, the
kernel is kind of like the brain of
the operating system. And the
operating system is what connects your
hardware to your software, right?
So there's layers to it. But almost
every kernel is written in C code.
And so C is just another programming
language. You can take another class
at Utah State and learn C code.
What's interesting is that
Python is a derivative of C
code. So if you think about
languages that are spoken,
you know, a lot of languages
are derived from Latin.
So things like, I think,
Italian, Portuguese, Spanish,
there's probably more, but we use
a lot of Latin words to this day in
many of those languages. And similarly,
you can trace a lot of coding
languages back to C code, C++,
Python, a lot of others. They're all
derivatives of C. And what's interesting
about that is that they all run,
these different languages, all run
really well on C-based operating systems.
So if your kernel is written in C
code, a lot of other applications
that are written in any other coding
languages that are derived from C
will work really well on your computer.
So we're going to be coding in
Python this semester, and it runs really
well on these three main operating
systems, Linux, Windows, and mac
os so each of them will have kind
of like their own differences and
whatnot but at the end of the day the
code will run really well on each
of those different operating systems
now some of you might be wondering
you might also not be wondering
what's to stop somebody else from
coming along and building another
operating system a fourth one if you
will and really the answer is nothing
there could be another operating
system that comes out tomorrow that
knocks all these other guys out of
the park. But until that happens,
it hasn't happened yet. So that
about wraps up this section on
operating systems. Please let me know
if you have any questions. Thanks.